Committee of Correspondence Records, 1952-1989 (bulk 1952-1971)
Sophia Smith Collection
Committee of Correspondence records
1952-1989
1952-1971
Committee of Correspondence
MS 340
57 boxes (26.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
International women's organization. The records include extensive official correspondence (1952-69) as well as hundreds of letters to and from correspondents throughout the world documenting the work of the organization. In addition there are official records; minutes; complete files of multi-lingual publications entitled "Community Action Series" and "Meeting Community Needs;" miscellaneous publications; conferences and workshop material; circa 150 photographs; oral history transcripts, 1988-89, with related biographical material and writings by individuals; and card files on individual participants, filed by country. The country files also contain published materials pertaining to the status and problems of the world's women.
The Committee of Correspondence was an American women's internationalist organization that started in New York City in 1952 and disbanded in 1969. A group of women active in internationalist voluntary clubs and professional fields created the Committee as an offshoot of the National Council of Women. The Committee established itself as an independent non-profit organization shortly after it began. Oriented toward anti-communism, the organization convened its first meeting in 1952 to answer the question, "what steps should be taken to rally the women of the free world to counteract communist propaganda?" However, its anti-communism was not conservative McCarthyism. It was among mid-century initiatives designed to counteract the perceived threat of international communism by promoting democratic, putatively American values in foreign countries. Over time, the Committee evolved into a communications network that aimed to bring women's clubs around the world into closer contact. The Committee sought to make an impact on a diverse international network of clubwomen and professionals. Its efforts promoted cooperation across national borders and encouraged the development of women's non-governmental organizations affiliated with the United Nations.
An advisory organization rather than a membership group, the Committee consisted of a governing board of roughly a dozen women and a small paid staff, which, at times, included field workers who carried out Committee projects in foreign countries. Committee members included Smith College alumnae Susan McKeever, Jean Picker, and Eleanor Coit. The Committee sought "to provide an international communications link for the exchange of ideas, information and experience among women leaders throughout the world." It did so by cultivating contacts with "correspondents," representatives of women's groups from around the globe who subscribed to the organization's newsletter and participated in its conferences and educational initiatives. Ultimately, five thousand women in 140 countries participated in Committee ventures.
The Committee was named after the associations through which American Revolution leaders shared information and created alliances across geographical divides. The term evoked the values of democratic participation that members identified with the American Revolution as well as with their own anti-communist project. It also made reference to writing as a form of communication that connected far-flung people. At the same time that the organization identified itself with American patriotism, the Committee of Correspondence embodied many dimensions of twentieth-century international women's movements. As with the women's rights movement of the nineteenth century, correspondence and publications created a network among women for whom face-to-face contact was difficult. The group reflected a transition from an internationalism spearheaded by women's voluntary clubs, which came to the forefront at the turn-of-the-century, to that in which professionally administered non-governmental organizations came to predominate.
The membership of the Committee of Correspondence was largely white and elite. Well-situated women active in voluntary clubs-including Constance Forrest Anderson, a leader in the Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A., and Rose Parsons, an officer of the International Council of Women-were able to donate considerable time to the organization. Others-notably Eunice Carter and Dorothy Height, both officers of the National Council of Negro Women, as well as Eleanor Coit, like Height, a long-time employee of the Young Women's Christian Association-had professional leadership roles in other such groups. The Committee attracted correspondents who were elite volunteers or middle-class professionals. Such women were able to travel internationally and often receptive to the anti-communist tenor of the Committee.
Many of the publications disseminated by the Committee, particularly its monthly bulletin, were culled from American sources, and its conferences and exchanges were administered by Committee members, rather than the correspondents. This was indicative of mid-century American Cold War conceptions of international development, the presumption that Americans had particular qualities for leadership that they hoped to instill among what was understood to be underdeveloped peoples. At the same time, correspondents and participants influenced the Committee's agenda as they provided their own perspectives on community development and international relationships in responses to publications and conferences. Their visions of an international women's movement at times converged with those of the Committee; at others, they clashed. Though the organization did not have a particularly prominent profile, its work attracted the interest of women active in politics, club work, and the media throughout the world.
While the organization was a product of Cold War liberalism, one its more influential lines of work pointed to an emergent model of internationalism based more on empowering the grassroots and facilitating small-scale community development rather than middle-class uplift. In the early 1960s the Committee hired field workers for short term programs in leadership and skills training for community leaders in foreign countries. Sarale Owens, a former YWCA executive, earned considerable acclaim during her two years spent in East Africa as a Committee field worker. The Committee also sent personnel to Latin America.
Despite the Committee's successes at promoting contacts among women's organizations and hosting conferences both in and out of the United States, it could not recover from revelations published in Ramparts magazine in 1967 that it was among the international organizations covertly funded by the Central Intelligence Agency. Supportive of the Committee's commitment to liberal anti-communism, the CIA had funneled funding for the Committee through private foundation grants. The degree to which the CIA had an influence on the Committee's programming is disputed. Some members were in contact with CIA agents; others were not aware of such activities. Several Committee efforts were directed at countries of special interest to the CIA. These included a 1961 conference for Latin American journalists that coincided with the Bay of Pigs invasion. Another was a 1963 conference in Iran on the "Role of Women in the Community." The event garnered the participation of Ashraf Pahlavi, twin sister to Mohammed Reza Pahlavi, the Shah who had taken power after the 1953 CIA-sponsored coup.
After the expose in Ramparts, which was further publicized in a series of New York Times articles, President Lyndon Johnson curtailed CIA funding of private foundations. Unable to fill the breach through traditional fundraising methods, the Committee of Correspondence elected to dissolve in 1969.
The Committee of Correspondence Records consist of 26.5 linear feet of organizational materials, dating from 1952 to 1989. Most records date from the 1950s to the 1960s. They include voluminous correspondence and reports generated by members' travel.
This collection is organized into eight series:
I. ADMINISTRATION (1952-69)
II. PUBLICATIONS (1953-70)
III. CONFERENCES, SEMINARS, AND WORKSHOPS (1956-68)
IV. INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS (1953-69)
V. CORRESPONDENTS AND FIELD WORK (1953-69)
VI. PHOTOGRAPHS (1953-62)
VII. ORAL HISTORIES (1987-89)
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the exception of original audiotapes; access copies must be made.
Additional Formats
This collection has been digitized and is available online (with database subscription)
The Committee of Correspondence donated its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1969.
Anti-communist movements--United States--History--Sources; Cold War; International relations -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Leadership in women--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Non-governmental organizations--United States; Propaganda, Anti-communist--History--Sources; Women -- Asia -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Women -- Europe -- Social conditions -- 20th century -- Sources; Women in community development -- International cooperation; Women in development -- International cooperation; Women -- International cooperation -- History -- Sources; Women -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies and clubs -- History -- Sources; Women's rights -- Developing countries -- History -- Sources; Women -- South America -- Social conditions -- 20th century -- Sources
Related materials might be found in the papers of Committee of Correspondence members held by the SSC, among them, Eleanor Gwinell Coit, Dorothy Irene Height, Elisabeth Luce Moore, Jean L. Noble, Jean Picker, and Alice Mayer Stetten, as well as records of the Pan Pacific Southeast Asia Women's Association and YWCA of the U.S.A.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1952-69, 2.5 linear ft.
  This series documents the management of the Committee of Correspondence. It contains legal and financial materials, including records pertaining to the charitable foundations through which CIA funding was channeled. There are also records of the committees that oversaw projects as well as files containing biographical information about members.
- SERIES II. PUBLICATIONS1953-70, 1.5 linear ft
  This series contains newsletters and books produced by the Committee of Correspondence. Publishing was a major avenue of activity for the organization. From 1953 to 1969 the Committee issued a monthly bulletin reporting on UN efforts, women's community development projects, and international cooperation. Many of these bulletins were translated into foreign languages; a full run of the bulletin and a sampling of foreign translations can be found in this series. Other publications, which built on similar themes pertinent to international women's organizations, include booklets and directories.
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES, SEMINARS, AND WORKSHOPS 1956-68, 1.5 linear ft.
  This series documents another set of activities central to the group: the meetings it sponsored for the purposes of information-sharing and training in non-profit techniques. These events ranged from a large, royally sponsored conference in Tehran in 1963, which brought together representatives of women's organizations from throughout the Middle East, to the intimate luncheons held in New York for women delegates to the United Nations.
- SERIES IV. INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS 1953-69, 1 linear ft.
  This series contains subject files pertaining to Committee contacts with internationally oriented organizations. The records include printed materials, reports, and correspondence. Researchers may also wish to consult the relevant country files in SERIES V. CORRESPONDENTS AND FIELD WORK, which also document the Committee's organizational relationships.
- V. CORRESPONDENTS AND FIELD WORK 1953-69, 17.5 linear ft.
  Materials in this series focus on two overlapping areas of Committee activity: the field work that sent paid staff to foreign countries and communications with the "correspondents" who received the organization's publications, participated in its conferences, or expressed interest in its work. These materials further document methods by which an American advisory group cultivated international relationships, revealing the Committee's strategies and impact on women's internationalism. Materials that originated with women and organizations from outside of the United States are included here. Organized by region, the series contains reports and correspondence from field workers who carried out training programs and organized conferences. The efforts of Sarale Owens, a field worker in East Africa, were most prominent in this regard. General files organized by country contain correspondence, reports and printed materials from the Committee's correspondents and contacts. A large set of note cards contain contact information and notes.
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS1953-62, .5 linear ft.
  A general collection of photographs, some of which document Committee events, comprise this series. Photographs can also be found interspersed throughout SERIES III. CONFERENCES, SEMINARS, AND WORKSHOPS and V. CORRESPONDENTS AND FIELD WORK.
- SERIES VII. ORAL HISTORIES 1987-89, 1.5 linear ft.
  This series is the result of Jacqueline Van Voris' research into the Committee of Correspondence. Van Voris, working on behalf of the Sophia Smith Collection, completed a set of taped interviews with Committee members in 1987-88. She used the histories as source material for her 1989 booklet, The Committee of Correspondence: Women with a World View. Interviewees discuss the vision of the organization, detail its projects, and assess its influence. Members also speak candidly about relationships with the Central Intelligence Agency and the effect of its involvement on organizational life. The histories are transcribed and well-indexed. The series also contains subject materials pertaining to Committee members and copies of Van Voris' publication.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, .5 linear ft.
  Oversize materials include inscribed books, awards, photographs, and a scrapbook, have been boxed separately for preservation purposes.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION
  - Affiliation, purpose, and by-laws, 1954-67 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual and quarterly reports, 1953-67 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Brochures, 1959-67 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1957-61 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Visitors log and reports, 1959-68 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) allegations, [see also Financial materials, Fundraising - Foundations, and SERIES VII. ORAL HISTORIES]
    - Memos, correspondence, notes, and statements, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Organization dissolution
    - General: legal and financial, 1968-71 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Final communications to correspondents, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence responding to closing, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence received subsequent to closure, general, 1969-71 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Financial materials
    - Accounting audits, 1954-68 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Budgets, statements, and leases, 1954-69 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tax exemption and charitable organization filings, 1956-68 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fundraising
    - Reports, memos, and notes, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and appeals, general, 1964-67 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Proposals, 1960-68 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Foundations and funders
      - Lists, 1960-67 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, general, A-Z (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
      - Agency for International Development, 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Dearborn Foundation, 1954-65 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
      - Florence Foundation, 1954-68 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Ford Foundation, 1959-68 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Hugh More Fund, 1958-68 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Institute for International Order, 1958-68 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Committees: minutes, memos, and reports
    - Assignment lists, 1960-67 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Africa, 1963-67 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
    - Asia, 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Budget, 1954-67 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Bulletin/Editorial, 1960-68 (Box 3, Folder 10-13)
    - Committee/Board/Corporation (governing committees)
      - 1952-68 (Box 4, Folder 1-12)
      - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Communications/Group Mailing, 1962-65 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Community Action Series, 1964-69 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Future Plans, 1967-68 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Latin America/Latin American Seminar, 1963-67 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Long Range Planning, 1958-66 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
    - Mid-East/North Africa, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Services to Correspondents, 1965-67 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Training/Evaluation/Kits, 1961-64 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Members and staff
    - Handbooks, policies, and job descriptions, 1956-66 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Training materials, 1959-63 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Nominations, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Biographies, 1952-64 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, general, outgoing, 1966-69 (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
    - Member files: miscellaneous correspondence, reports, clippings, and photographs
      - Anderson, Constance (Mrs. Arthur Forrest), 1958-59 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Backus, Louise (Mrs. Dana), 1956-64 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Bauman, Dorothy (Mrs. John Sprague), 1952-68 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Clark, Alice (Mrs. Lincoln), 1962-68 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Coit, Eleanor, 1953-68 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Cross, Una (Mrs. A.J. Foy), 1962-67 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Dermady, Ethel (Mrs. Stephen), 1963-64 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Harris, Rosalind (Mrs. Michael), 1958-65 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Height, Dorothy, 1956-68 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Herzog, Julie (Mrs. Paul) [Julie Chamberlain d'Estournelles], 1955-62 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Jackson, Elizabeth (Mrs. Elmore), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Mahon, Charlotte (Mrs. Burnett), 1953-65 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - McKeever, Susan (Mrs. Porter), 1959-68 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Nielsen, Marcia (Mrs. Waldemar), 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Papanek, Betka (Mrs. Jan), 1958-68 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Parsons, Rose (Mrs. William Barclay), 1956-68 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Picker, Jean (Mrs. Harvey), 1958-68 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Raymond, G. Alison, 1959-60 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Russell, Polly (Mrs. John), 1961-68 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Shattuck, Ruth (Mrs. Howard), 1966 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Sherbert, Marjorie (Mrs. Paul), 1960-68 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Simms, Ruth (Mrs. Albert), 1967 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Strauss, Anna Lord, 1953-66 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Walls, Esther, 1965-67 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Washburne, Elizabeth (Mrs. George), 1959-66 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Associate member files
      - Bornholdt, Laura, 1960-69 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Carter, Eunice (Mrs. Lisle), 1956-67 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Kenyon, Mildred (Mrs. W. Houston), 1956-69 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Moore, Elizabeth Luce (Mrs. Maurice), 1958-68 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Noble, Jeanne, 1962-67 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Padover, Peg Fenwick (Mrs. Saul), 1961-66 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Page, Jane (Mrs. Walter), 1959-67 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Singer, Jeanne, 1961-67 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Stetten, Alice (Mrs. DeWitt), 1958-68 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Teltsch, Kathleen, 1956-67 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- SERIES II. PUBLICATIONS
  - Information sheet and title list, 1950s-69 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Copyright, permissions, and reprints, 1962-68 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondent responses, 1963-68 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Group mailings, general, including "colonialism" mailing and response, 1961-62 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Booklets, 1962-64 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bulletins
    - Published, 1953-69 (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
    - Duplicate set, 1953-69 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Translations (sampling)
      - Arabic (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - French (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - German (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Greek (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Italian (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Japanese (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Portuguese (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Spanish (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Community Action Series
    - Permissions and inquiries, 1964-67 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Loose copies, 1964-67 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Bound copies, 1964-67 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Bound volume: Community Action, ed. H. Elsie Austin, 1970 (English/French reprint of Community Action Series for use in Africa) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Meeting Community Needs," undated
    - Index, questionnaire, and lists (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Mailings (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Volunteers Can Make a Difference": booklet, correspondence, and notes, 1963-65 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Women's International Non-Governmental Organizations Directory," 1962-69 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- SERIES III. CONFERENCES, SEMINARS, AND WORKSHOPS
  - General, 1956-63 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Reports, conferences attended by Committee members, 1958-68, [see also SERIES V. CORRESPONDENTS AND FIELD WORK] (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Asian workshop, 1956: "The Responsibilities of Freedom" (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Asian workshop, 1957: "The Role of Women in the Community" (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Luncheon for Women Delegates to the United Nations General Assembly, 1957-68 (Box 12, Folder 5-8)
  - "Moslem" workshop: "The Role of Women in the Community and the Home" 1958: (Box 12, Folder 9-10)
  - UN and consular wives from the Middle East and North Africa workshop, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Moslem" workshop: "The Role of Women in the Community and the Home" 1959
    - Planning materials (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Conference materials and follow-up (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - New York City workshop: "Women's Opportunity in the New Decade" 1960
    - Essay contest, general (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Essay submissions (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - "Women Are People" booklet (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Conference material and follow-up (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Workshop guest notebook (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Multi-nation Project in Civic Responsibility and Leadership, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Proposed Icelandic workshop, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Small seminars, Okinawa, 1960-61 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Press/Radio Seminar, 1961
    - Planning (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Conference materials and follow-up (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Vassar College, 1961: "Emerging Values and New Directions: Their Implications for Education" (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Eisenhower Fellowship Fund Wives' Seminar, 1961-64 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Women's International Non-Governmental Organizations (WINGO) Conference, 1962
    - Planning (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
    - Conference materials and photos (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Iran: "The Role of Women in the Community" 1963, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
    - Planning (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Conference materials (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Follow-up (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Latin American Seminar, 1963
    - Planning (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Committee minutes (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Applicants and participants (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - "What Makes a Vigorous Society?" addresses (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Photographs (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Conference materials and follow-up (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - WINGO Seminar, 1964-65 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- SERIES IV. INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS
  - Afro-American Institute (U.K.), 1960 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Asian-African Conference of Women, 1957-61 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Associated Country Women of the World, 1953-69 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Institute of International Education, 1956-68 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Inter-American Commission of Women, 1960-68 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - International Advisory Council, 1957-63 (Box 15, Folder 8)